what to
B e
it's only one object in the world is
your
breath e
come to the golden
room
e e
don't let your mind leave the Goen room
look at the sky outside the
window e
stay with this guy be contented to stay
with this guy
then drop your gaze to the mountains
across the
valley lit with the last Light of the
day e
and bring your mind into the golden
room ask your dear sweetheart teacher to
come and feel their hands on your hands
that's all
the meditation
object is the touch of their hand on
your hand focus on
that keep the mind there not with a
struggle but by
enjoying this sacred touch on your head
don't lose the touch on your hands use
your iron hook in your
chain bring the Mind back
and enjoy
the only thing in the world is the touch
of your teacher's hand e
turn to your teachers here
then bring yourself back to this
room slowly open your eyes
uh in my experience
uh with the few hours after meals is not
a good time to meditate it's difficult
it's like yoga and
uh I don't know
for I think for
about 15 years I didn't eat dinner I
didn't eat afternoon or I didn't eat
after lunch uh and so evening was a
pretty good time to meditate
but
uh but in threee Retreat we found out
that the quality of meditation degrades
very
quickly uh as you get closer to bedtime
okay like it just goes down very sharply
the length of time you can meditate goes
down very
sharply I don't know in the evening for
most
people so don't fight it you know don't
try I don't what we've been trying to do
this week was to start with a very short
high quality
meditation and not not worry about the
length of the meditation we weren't
trying to pile up minutes meditating we
were we were trying to make it high
quality and then the length will come by
itself you see it did today right this
afternoon it came by itself we weren't
trying I didn't set a goal to like oh
let's increase it to 20 25 minutes or
something but it came because the
quality was good okay so if you I don't
know about you just now I felt the
quality wasn't so good for myself and
then I was like oh I'll fight this you
know and I I'm going to not stop before
20 minutes or 25 minutes and then that's
a bad idea okay if it's if you're tired
if you just ate if it's been a long day
if you still have part of a
cold uh then wrap it up you know and get
to bed early you know take care of
yourself and and have a better one
tomorrow
okay don't don't uh what I mean is don't
get in the habit of having a bad
meditation a don't get in the habit of
having a lowquality meditation because
that's what happens to almost everybody
who tries to meditate they just they go
on for an hour and it's all low quality
and then they get used to it and then
they don't really ever have good
meditations they don't know what it even
feels like you know so
say oh you can't
say they call
koaa the people on the CH turn know KOA
KOA means the
idiot UK means
uh
insistence idiot
insistence so Koop don't do Koop U with
your meditation you know don't just sit
there and say I'm going to go for 10:00
whether I whether I'm on the object or
off you know that's like the opposite
stay on the object and then you know if
it's 10 minutes okay if it's an hour
okay if it's 5 minutes okay just stay on
the object if you find you can't stay on
the object then
stop because it just gets a bad habit it
gets subtle dullness or gross dullness
or probably even forgetting the
object like I think in a lot of cases it
gets worse than dullness what's worse
than bonus just losing the object just
spending the whole meditation time
thinking about something
else and then you get in that habit and
then you sit down to meditate you close
your eyes and you start thinking about
something else right away cuz you have
the habit of it you know and then you
stop even noticing that you're off the
object I'm speaking from personal
experience okay all right uh here we go
[Music]
so okay Nick
uh so he's not he's not the Nick if he's
not the Nick if he's not the one Nick
who is the some total of his Parts which
we already we just finished that that
was Point number three three so we're on
to point number four is Nick his Parts
is Nick somehow divorced from his Parts
is there a Nick who's independent from
his part
okay uh so here we
go I should rather say who is his Parts
but here we
go once you get it straight that there
can't be just one big Nick and
well then you might figure to yourself
well if there's not one big
Nick uh who owns the parts then I guess
he would have to be the parts themselves
okay if there's not a Nick who owns the
body and owns the mind then I guess the
body and the mind must be Nick okay the
plural the plurality is Nick okay
and do
means uh it couldn't rightfully be
anything else W normally means uh to be
worthy okay W shoke is uh a ballot a
voting ballet a worthiness
paper okay uh all right so do means it
wouldn't be
right nothing else would be right except
for Nick to be plural if he he weren't
the big boss of all his Parts
okay cuz he's got to be related to the
parts somehow if he's either related to
the parts or he's not related to the
parts if he's related to the parts and
he's not the big boss then he can only
be the parts
okay so suppose then
that uh there is a a neck who was
separate from its parts okay
rude text on wisdom
says it's not correct to say that Nick
could be anything separate from his
Parts okay it's not correct to say that
Nick could be anything separate from his
Parts uh the parts in the word for parts
here being that which he took on at
Birth the parts which he took on at
Birth if Nick Were Somehow separate uh
from the parts which he took on at Birth
then there wouldn't have been any taking
and there wouldn't have been any
holding uh because there would be
nothing to hold right so that's the the
that's
our here's the explanation of
it this is you know I don't know if you
appreciate what to is the repository of
the highest knowledge of mankind for the
last Thousand Years okay seriously and
uh before Buddhism got there they were
all Yak hurters okay there was
no writing they didn't have a written
language uh they were all just uh
sitting on the sides of uh you know
Barren 25,000 ft high mountain you know
rocks heating hurting a few goats and
sheep and Yaks and that was it
so
uh a lot of the examples you find in
scripture relate to Critters
okay uh so ra Lum suppose you got a A
goat a sheep and a cow okay suppose you
got a goat a sheep and a cow and then uh
you take out the goat and sheep well
what do you got
left you guessed it a
cow sh uh so like if you got these three
Critters and you take away two of them
then you end up with a count right so uh
but is it also that way with the five
parts to a person's personal you know
the person what are the five parts we'll
go over them one more time
like right so Suk means uh the physical
parts of a person which are the body of
the person okay the the physical parts
of a person so is the first scand or or
Heap why are they called heaps why are
the parts of a person called
heaps first chapter
ofha uh they're called heaps because
they are piles of different things like
the the Heap of the body is composed of
all the arms and leg and you know it's a
a pile of stuff so they're called piles
or
scas uh we're just saying parts of the
person okay but be aware that each part
is made of many components and that's
why they're called
piles so could you do the same exercise
with the five parts of a person well
let's do the five parts your physical
body your
feelings uh Your Capacity to divide
between things or discriminate between
things okay number three number four
your other the other function FS of your
mind which are you know what are they uh
51 or depends on what school you're in
46 something I think that's it uh there
are certain functions of the
mind so then the obida says why did they
take two of the functions out and make
them separate heaps why did they just
say body and mind why did they say body
and feelings
discrimination other functions of the
mind and Consciousness why did they
split them
[Music]
out that's the first chapter of also uh
we separate out two of the heaps feeling
and
discrimination because they are the
cause of of our
suffering I I I like how that feels so I
like him I like him because he makes me
feel good I don't like her because she
doesn't make me feel good okay so we
divide based on feelings we make
discriminations based on feelings so
because
those because those two mental functions
are the root of all
suffering they are in the study of the
parts of person they are separated out
into their own categories because
they're so important in causing
suffering so is it the case that as we
did with the Sheep the goat and the cow
that we could
just take out of the room the body the
feelings the Discrimination the other
mental functions and and raw awareness
itself and then would we find
Nick okay that's the question is there a
Nick which is separate from his
pieces okay and we're getting more
sophisticated then saying Nick and his
arms and legs right we're saying Nick
his body his feelings his capacity to
discriminate the other parts of his mind
and his his capacity for awareness at
all okay if we strip away the five parts
the five classical parts of a
person will we find Nick will Nick be
left over in the way that the cow is
left over when we take away the goat and
the Sheep that's all got it
okay yeah aasha is saying no it doesn't
work that way it's not the case there
doesn't so the Argo there doesn't seem
to be an independent Nick who is who is
independent from his Parts okay because
it's not like the sheep and the goat and
the cow
okay which reminds me of the rabbi and
the Goat story but we don't have time
for that there's lots of good stories in
the diamond business uh
[Music]
so you would expect that if
Nick Were Somehow if there were a
separate Nick who owned his Parts
because that's what we really think
right Nick's leg Nick's ear Nick's mind
then Nick must be something different
than Nick's ear right he must somehow be
the possessor of all of them right so
but if we eliminate one by one all those
parts then we try to find a nict we
can't find one
okay
okay then he starts listing problems
with this idea that uh there's a Nick
who is separate from his part
okay if if Nick were something other
than his five classical
Parts uh then he would lack the defining
quality the defining characteristics of
those parts okay what does that mean
here's the explanation and you have to
know AB D to appreciate it
[Music]
so in the Dharma they
describe the defining characteristics of
a changing thing okay the the defining
characteristics of a changing thing
changing things are big in Buddhism
right the because everything's changing
everything's impermanent right so there
are certain qualities that if you see
them in a you can say it's unchanging
all all changing things exhibit certain
qualities okay what are they here are
some
uh starting and stopping starting and
stopping then he said laa and you got to
really appreciate that he's a master of
Abid Dharma he said said and so
on uh because in Abid Dharma there's a
big debate uh because some schools of
ABI Dharma say all changing things
exhibit three modes
starting staying and stopping and then
some more radical Abid Dharma schools
say come
on things don't really stay do they at
for even an instant there's no stay
there's just starting and stopping
okay and then people say oh well Buddha
taught that there were three starting
staying and stopping and then and then
the reply comes well he was just trying
not to freak people
out okay but in truth everything is
dying from the moment it
starts okay everything is stopping from
the moment it starts every the starting
of a thing kills it the starting of the
birth of a human being kills the human
being you know
so so Buddha was careful not to not to
emphasize thing cuz people would get
complacent they'd say well at least I
can stay for a while you know but then
Buddha said let's cut out the
stain cuz lots of kids die in the womb
they don't get to stay okay like that
okay so
anyway then there's beautiful debates in
the ab if you really want to know which
you don't but it's okay
about whether the starting has a
starting and a
stopping and whether the starting stat
at all and then they it gets pretty wild
but I won't go
there
so I in the G is saying if you were
separate from your parts if there were a
Nick that we could find after we had
taken away the sheep and the cow you
know sheep and the Goat if there a Nick
that we could find like that then he
wouldn't exhibit the qualities that his
Parts exhibit meaning he wouldn't stop
and start he would be eternally there he
would never get more or less Nick okay
because he's independent from those
changing things you take away the
changing things he's still there like
the cow is still there after you take
away the sheep and the Goat okay so then
his nature would be radically different
from the nature of his Parts the nature
of his Parts is to exhibit
these defining qualities of a changing
thing starting stopping thing so if he
were completely independent of those
parts it'd be like what the when my mom
used to say soul your
soul and then you'd say Mom what do you
mean by soul and they would say well
it's a part it's a part of you inside of
you that doesn't change and it goes to
heaven after you die so that's how I was
brought up I don't know how you heard
soul I don't know what kind of Soul
thing you they gave you that's the one I
got and uh you know what I had a feeling
for a long time about what my soul was
it was like a a core of my
being and like a little Stone inside my
body and you know that would not die
when the body died like that would there
was a part of me that was a core part of
me that was still
Mike uh that after I died it would be
safe somewhere and it would go somewhere
and you know eternally be okay uh so
this Nick begins to sound a little bit
like that I think if you say he's not if
you say there's a Nick Beyond his mind
and body then I guess you could might
say so and and it would also not exhibit
the qualities of
mortality and the qualities of uh you
know worldly impermanence it it would be
somehow
transcendant
from from
the slings and arrows of Outrageous
Fortune you know what I mean it would be
above all that and it wouldn't change
okay so it's similar to what we're
saying here if there were a
Nick that you could find after you took
away all his changing parts
then that Nick would have to be like
unchanging Eternal would not exhibit the
qualities of
mortality also since you're the parts of
Any Given person exhibit the qualities
of the famous Buddhist qualities of
Kachi so say Kachi in your mind
okay oh you got the chi
wrong G okay Kachi is very very famous
uh these are the four sufferings of life
okay K is to be born to be born is
suffering you don't remember cuz it's
been a while but it was a hassle okay
they were squishing your head and
everything
uh g g is uh getting old which started
the day you were you were born now the
the illness that comes to people
sickness and then CH death so these are
the four Great sufferings that that
Buddha Lord Buddha came to to help us
overcome if
Nick were totally divorced and
independent of his
parts then since the those parts have Ki
he wouldn't have Kachi cuz he's
radically different he's radically above
he transcends his Parts he owns the
parts Nick's body Nick's mind so Nick is
some kind of
Eternal you know unchanging crystalline
thing I used to think his soul is
crystalline a little bit and he's like
some crystallin thing and he would not
exhibit Kachi okay Nick
Nick would never die Nick would never
get old Nick would never get sick his
body would and his mind would but since
he is separate from them and transcends
them and owns them he wouldn't exhibit
this okay Nick's body would get all but
Nick wouldn't all
right also this is very famous
in in examining the relationship between
things okay uh pen means either help or
hurt and often times it's physical okay
so pen would be like uh give somebody a
massage no would be
like punching them okay so if Nick were
substantially independent or different
from Nick's parts then you could stick a
knife in the body and it wouldn't hurt
Nick cuz they're not related
substantially okay or you could uh give
a massage to the body and Nick wouldn't
necessarily feel
good cuz Nick's is above all them Nick
Nick owns the body and he's separate
from the body so if the body if you you
could hurt or harm his body and Nick
wouldn't feel anything either way if he
were essentially separate from
his body and mind which we've decided is
necessary because we we just we we
already decided he wasn't the same as
okay if you remember
okay you can look this part over again
for about 23 years and uh you'll figure
it
out this is very very important for
those of you who want to be you know you
want to understand scripture you got to
learn this expression okay
means the world Loca J is a translation
of
Loca which comes from roach which means
to shine okay they're they're from the
same R okay and roach so uh so I guess
Sanskrit was invented by a a Thai person
but
anyway
uh Jen
means no I add office in Thailand I had
a starting office in Thailand and we had
three main suppliers of rubies and
sapphires and they were real gems Lear
gems and rare gems but when the
secretary called me she'd say l Little
Gems is
here cuz all the RS and L's are you know
L gems so I'd say which L gems you know
so
anyway RS and L's are are what do you
call in in
interchangeable in Sanskrit in general
they're interchangeable in Sans okay so
anyway Mel means
uh means
loc means in the par of the world okay
in the parlament of the world parlance
is a really beautiful word for Tanya
here in the normal speech of the world
in the normal usage of the
world uh
we say things
like uh Nick got sick or we say uh Nick
got CAU right and we say things like uh
Nick has changed since yesterday and we
say things like Nick was born so in the
parlament of the world uh we can say
those
things but that doesn't mean that the
word Nick got old
or the word Nick got caught or the word
Nick you know exhibited the quality of
starting or stopping you see what I mean
uh in in the way we normally view
Nick you could say Nick got caught but
then you don't see Nick change to ick
you see what I mean no I'm serious I'm
serious when you say Nick got cut you
mean Nick's body got cut right you don't
mean Nick got cut
right
uh Nick is something else right when you
think about it it's not that Nick got
cut it's that Nick's body got cut okay
or when you say Nick got upset it's not
that Nick got upset it's Nick's mind got
upset
okay if Nick was body and mind together
then when Nick got upset his body would
have get upset or when you cut his
finger he'd forget six
words you see what I mean
seriously okay so he's not his body and
mind aren't mixed together but we tend
to think there's some kind of Nick above
his body and mind who owns them and and
we think of that Nick as as undamageable
you don't say ick or Nick got CAU you
know like that Nick Nick is the same
Nick Nick is a word Nick is an idea and
Nick lasts from the time he's born to
the time he dies and and you don't
change the word you don't call him Nick
in 1983 or Nick in 1996 you know it's
just
Nick okay he's going to get sick of this
anyway
uh
pil shil no so anyway you are
contradicting the parlament of the
world if you say that
uh if you go around saying Nick's body
got hurt Nick's body got cut right the
the common parlance of the world says
what Nick got cut okay and that implies
some kind of connection between Nick and
his
Parts because actually only his body got
cut okay so you say we don't have to say
Nick's body got cut we just say Nick got
cut because everybody understands that
Nick's body is part of Nick or Nick's
body is Nick but then this this the guy
who's presenting part four he he said I
decided that Nick is separate from his
part then you would be contradicting how
the whole world talks about Nick very
very very very famous okay
uh you're all too young was anybody
around during
Woodstock okay
anyway so there's this guy Max yasgar
right is very famous there you know they
expected like a couple hundred people to
show up at at this rock festival and
then a million or something showed up
like a half a million people showed up
and they all took off their clothes and
smoked don't and stuff like that and
then they were having a really good time
and then
uh this guy got up the guy who owned the
they did it they they held an event on
some farmlands some Meadows some huge
Meadows and uh so I don't I know why
they were bored between Acts or
something and uh somebody put the guy
the owner of the farm they got him up on
the microphone to say hi and he's got
these suspenders on and he's this old
chubby fat guy you know and and he gets
up after Jimmy Hendrickson before Janice
jlin you know and he he grabs the mic
and he says I'm he's scared to death you
know he's like half a million people are
staring at him and he's and he's like
I'm Max
I'm a farmer and then
everybody they Roar you know they they
Roar for him you
know why am I talking about
that
uh somebody asked Aran a guarder one
time uh what school of philosophy do you
represent and he said I'm a
farmer that's all he said
I'm a
farmer and then people said what do you
mean and he said whatever Farmers say I
also say you know what do farmers say
theard Farmers say if you plant a seed a
plant will grow that's it nothing more
complicated than that I'm a farmer
whatever farmer say I say too and I'm
never going to contradict the farmers
you know don't expect me to contradict a
farmer whatever a farmer says is okay
with me
you know and then people were just blown
away they were hoping for some you know
new new school of philosophy and all he
said was I go along with whatever
Farmers
say that's called jigang that's the par
of what he meant with parliament of the
world if a farmer says a a plant grows
from a seed I also use that language and
I believe it you know if a if if people
in the world choose to say Nick nick. C
rather than saying Nick's body got cut
that's fine with me and you shouldn't
contradict the Pence of the world or or
you're getting unreal so here it
says
means contct okay so if you if you if
you try to say there's a
Nick who's independent of his body in
mind uh then you're going to then you're
going to be disagreeing with farmers
you you the words the Expressions you
used and the words you Ed will
contradict the way Farmers talk and then
and that's not that's a an illusion to
Nar then then you're contradicting who I
mean you're basic if you contradict the
parlance of the world you are
contradicting the person who brought
emptiness to this world you know that's
what I mean if you know then that's
there there there a heavy accusation to
to say to somebody you are contradicting
the way the world
talks okay all right whatever you decide
whatever you come up
with in your search for Ultimate Reality
should be expressable in the common
words of the world or you have it
wrong okay you should be able to express
it in in common understandable language
like the pen thing you know uh without
reference to schools of philosophy in
fact in China we had this thing you we
can't be religious there uh we
can't I can't wear robes we can't talk
about religious subjects we have to
stick to business and
relationships but we speak about
emptiness extensively and we speak about
Karma extensively we don't use the
words uh and and people get it we are
just using the language of the world and
that's the way it should be okay anyway
if Nick if there was a Nick who owns his
body and mind then in a place where his
body and mind aren't we should be able
to have a Nick sometimes if we
want okay if he's if there's a Nick who
owns his body and mind which means who
is independent from his body and mind
then we could say Nick's over there even
when his body and mind are over here cuz
he's independent of them he doesn't
depend on them okay so you could say
next could be over there when his body
and mind are over here all right get I
should
do you would also have the logical what
do they call in English you can't say
logical problem right in is logical
problem
what uh you could also have a case where
uh a
person committed a Karma and never had
to experience its result it just went
away okay somebody did something and
there was
no what do you call it
payback a Karma without a
payback all right a boomerang that never
flew
back okay that that that's what you
would have if there were a Nick who
owned his body and mind separate from
his body and mind in the way that the
cow separate from the sheep and the Goat
okay also then there would have to be
Nicks who
encountered uh consequences of their
actions that they hadn't
committed consequences of actions that
they hadn't
committed which are both unfair and not
and not allowable
okay as we mentioned earlier okayi
n n is a good nice word N means
harmer and it means uh problems with a
position harmer means problems with a
position in in Buddhist logic okay
meaning uh if you say Nick is uh not his
body and mind if you say there's a big
Nick who owns his body and mind then uh
there's lots of things that hurt that
idea there's lots of there's lots of
things you could bring up that would
disprove that idea okay boy you guys are
sleepy it's going to get worse should I
do
this I think we'll keep
going so you should decide in your mind
right now that there's no Nick
who is separate from his body and mind
there isn't any name so we have a
problem here okay you have to try to
appreciate it these last few these are
hard and I'm I I went through them
because they're in the book If I Had You
know if I wasn't going straight through
a book I I would have skipped them or
something I I wouldn't have talked about
them but I feel like I'm supposed to be
giving you the whole transmission of a
certain book uh these these last few
pages are
very difficult and they it's hard to
make them relevant but what I would say
is go back to the pen somebody gave me a
pen uh go back to the pen just go back
to the pen when you're not sure go back
to the pen okay
uh is the pen coming that is the pen
coming that way or this
way yeah I'm I'm something in my mind is
creating the pen why cuz when a puppy
dog comes in they don't write with it or
they don't even try they just chew on it
okay so that means they don't see a
pen uh they see a chew toy right so it
means the pen is not announcing
itself uh it means the pen must be
coming from me okay just remember
that does it but does it appear
naturally to normal people people that
the pen is coming from the
pen the're normal people if I said uh is
is is pen is coming from the pen they
would say yeah they wouldn't say pen is
made up by my mind or something like
that okay if I held it up would I I'd
say is this a pen they'd say yeah it's a
pen I say where's it coming from they
say well it's just a pen it's coming
from itself you know uh they don't think
that they're creating the pen as they go
on the Fly what's that thing in
programming on the
Fly I think it's on the Fly it's doing
calculations on the Fly they don't think
it's your mind creating the thing on the
Fly okay but there does appear p a pen
that comes from its own side right that
now now get this I'm not going to let
you be sleepy okay get this uh there's
an appearance of a pen that comes from
its own side coming from the pen there
is an appearance
of a pen that came from its own side
that's flowing from the pen and from my
side there's an old bad habit that
accepts that appearance okay there's
something there's a lie coming from the
pen and there's an acceptance of the LIE
coming from me and they meet in the
middle somewhere and then I believe the
pen came from itself why does this
matter to
you the next person who yells at you
whether it's your spouse or your
llama
uh you have to think they're not coming
from themselves they're coming from me
why I must have yelled at someone before
and planted a seed in my mind and that's
why I see them yell well if you don't
like people yelling at you what should
you
do well you can start by not yelling
back
okay do you not yell back because it's a
noble thing not to yell back
no do you not yell back because they're
not stupid no they're
stupid okay all bosses and husbands are
stupid you
know okay you know that
uh it's just that if you call them
stupid then you'll have people calling
you stupid for for weeks so it's just a
matter of self-preservation it's not
it's not Noble or or right or moral or
it's just unpleasant to have people
yelling at you all the time so so don't
yell back
okay then you stop
them
anyway
so we've been
examining have we been examining whether
a a pen is the sum total of its parts
sorry have we been examining whether a
pen is
uh is it is the some collection of its
parts or whether it owns those parts or
something like have we been examining
that have we been in examining whether a
pen is related to its part be careful
[Laughter]
you got to go back to what we were
talking you see we're not actually
talking the question has not been for
these many painful
hours whether the
pen was the sum of its part that that
wasn't the question question was whether
what you think the pen is is the sum of
its
parts
okay you know the I'll say it again is
the pen which is coming from its own
side know I'm
already your mind should say your mind
should say right there your mind should
say but G that doesn't exist now you
want to examine how it relates to the
world you know how does an Hest
politician relate to the world you
know there's no use talking about it
there's no such thing okay so
we've been examining whether the pend
that comes from its own side was one
with its parts or wasn't one with these
parts and the whole discussion was was
fruitless because it doesn't exist okay
it can't be the same as his parts we can
discuss whether Nick has his Parts but
that's not what we've been discussing
we've been discussing whether the Nick
who came from his own side was one with
his part which is a useless
discussion because either way you either
way you take it it's going to be wrong
okay is is the Nick which comes from his
own side one thing or many things you
should
say okay it's a dumb question there's no
such
thing is a what's the example in
scripture two famous examples of
scripture is a rabbit with
antlers are the antlers on a rabbit's
head 6 in long or 12 in long and then
you should just
say
Okay is a flower which grows in midair
with no means of sustenance no Earth no
water no sunlight no sea does it smell
good or bad you see those are famous
examples in scripture what's our example
a Nick who came from his own side why
are we interested in that
because Nick got blamed for stealing
that's how he got here that's how he
can't this King Nick got blamed for
stealing books
okay and then they got and then Nick had
this big extra
Nick who didn't deserve to get
play right and that Nick was the same as
Casper the ghost there there was no Nick
like that and it got bigger and bigger
the more he got blamed for studying the
books okay does the Nick who got blamed
on
wrongly for stealing the books right is
he one with his parts or is he separate
from his
Parts yeah I mean gu just say mean the L
could you just put the other five pages
away like just take him out of the book
and uh future Generations won't have to
go through these two last couple days
we'll just put a little note there that
says you know this Nick never existed
anyway so we're going to skip the
discussion of whether he's one or or or
not with his Parts got it cuz if you're
going to look into whether Nick is one
with his Parts well then that's that's
he
is he is the sum of his Parts okay he is
there is a Nick which is the sum of his
Parts okay that's all but not not the
Nick that would didn't deserve to get
bled okay no such hopefully we're at the
end of these four parts let's see how we
doing on time m
am I supposed to stop at 9:30 right
no what's it say over there
9:30 does it say 9:30 okay let's do
let's do some questions okay and then
I'll hit you with some more let me see
if we got anything else here
[Music]
yeah let's let's stop there okay who's
picking is jelle
picking
okay this is a panda's
hat no uh seriously pan hat was design
with with a single point on the top
why it represents seagra that's why
those those skinny we call them dun
hats whoa that's a good
question can we uh there are nine levels
of meditation there are five problems in
meditation but nowhere in the poster did
they actually link the problems to this
you know the five problems in the N
States so could we do
that there's a reason why they
didn't let's
chat uh what's the first
problem is not feeling like
meditating which okay here's another
Nick
question here's another Nick question
which of the nine levels would that
relate
to be careful
where do you find the on which of the
nine levels do you not feel like
meditating again there's no such thing
because you're meditating by the first
the first level is is is you're already
in meditation very lousy poor fly on the
fly on the caline meditation but you're
meditating so to answer the question as
far as problem number one that happens
before the first level of meditation how
about the second problem which was
losing the object
completely that would happen all the way
up to what the fourth level or
something okay you would you would lose
the object completely but in
increasingly less
times in the first two stages you're off
it more than you're on it so problem
number two is occurring more than
problem number two is not occurring and
then when you get to level three it
starts to switch around okay how about
the third problem what's the third
problem
CH uh don't
listen all the way up to uh all the way
up to there right all the way up to
eight is it I think it's eight okay all
the way up to there you have them uh
churing the mental mode where you are
being harassed by uh and interrupted and
you know this thing by Don L I think
it's up to eight right uh what about
problem number three failing to take
action when you should have taken
action I would say we're still there
right you could still say it applies
even at 9
perhaps if it's action to fix dullness
and agitation then only up to
7 okay then what about uh over
overacting like like trying to trying to
fix it when it ain't
broken uh 7
and8 I think it could happen almost
anywhere no like you could be trying to
fix dullness when you don't have
dullness or something I don't know but
yeah mainly it's up high it's up around
8 and N when you're on cruise control
you shouldn't fool with the acceler
just leave things alone it's cruising at
its own speed so it's true that in the
scripture they don't actually do this
exercise and it's a smart question it's
a really good question it means the
person is thinking about uh about it
their handwriting looks to me
French am I right
okay there's a benefit to being on
planes all your life okay
let's do
yeah
gu okay let skip that
part yeah this is pretty
bad I like this one I'll do the whole
thing uh enormous thanks for your
inspirational guidance I will forever be
in your debt number two is it true that
you only rarely get past meditation
level number
three it gets better it gets better it
gets better it's really cute I suspect
that you are using this as an
educational technique to place yourself
at our level
however I personally find it
discouraging to that after 20 and 30
years of
[Applause]
medic it gets
better after 20 30 years of meditating
and then in parenthesis properly and
following the
instructions uh that I would still be at
level three and then it ends with should
I shoot myself
[Applause]
now I mean if you want me to be frank I
did have better meditation a long time
ago and I think it was Baka you see what
I mean it wasn't due to any efforts in
this life I I think I came in with
certain mental seeds and they typically
those kinds of
seeds ripen in the late teens and the
20s and and after that you're on you're
on your own meaning whatever efforts you
make in this time you see what I mean so
you get kind of
the the main deit
credit that if you've had a good pth
life then the main uh time that you
benefit from
that normally in many in many instant in
many aspects is is your late teens and
and your 20s and and then you you then
you're just running on the seeds that
you've created in this life and we don't
normally create great seeds
between you know in our high school
years say no seriously you it's not like
you spend your high school years in deep
meditation or something normally you are
enjoying the ripening of good seeds from
your P life so you drink and you party
and you meet girls and you see
that's good seeds ripening from your
past life but it's not creating any new
good seeds see that comes with just hard
work and the hard work doesn't start
until you start the Dharma right until
someone teaches you meditation and you
start working hard you running on P life
SE seeds mainly and and those were out
so in my personally in my own case I
think it was mostly past life sees that
I did have a extraordinary meditation in
my 20s and then after that I was on my
my current life Seas so I had to
overcome Washington High School
Seas uh seriously and I had to work back
to to to this to where I am now so I in
my own case that's what's happening
uh some of the seeds from my past life I
think are ripening now late and and very
beautiful important things are happening
but you know so so just be aware of that
with your own self uh you it's it's you
won't have great meditation until you've
had time to collect the seeds for it uh
and that will take some time okay
so all right so yes often times I am on
level three or
less cool uh
this is a a reaction to the statement
that you are creating the pages of the
book as you turn it right so if that's
true that as I turn the pages of a book
my mind is laying down the next Words
which is the C that's the
case uh then how did I come to write
this
book see why am I hearing this
book uh if I if I'm the
author uh how could I have written this
book cuz I don't understand
it something like that I mean it's there
high thoughts that I haven't thought
about in my life so how could it be that
I have written it um that's not a big
you know that's not a big problem right
like you you did some extraordinary
goodness one of the cool things about
seeing emptiness Direct L which is not
much talked
about is
uh is that the karma of seeing emptiness
directly assures that you will never be
without fantastic teachers ever
again okay
like that's one of the cool side what do
you call it side effects of seeing
emptiness directly it creates a special
Karma that you will never not be in the
hands of of a very very high teachers
you know
um but you see that's an example you
didn't go you didn't set out to create
the karma to be in the hands of high
teachers you did some extraordinary
goodness and that will manifest in
multiple different ways and one of them
is teachers who know more than you could
ever know okay and it's not that you
have to know that to manifest them okay
okay why the seed is you know
shika shika seed is always smaller than
the shika Chua means watermelon right is
very popular in the DCI talks in
China uh because people really relate to
watermelons in China people eat them
people eat them dessert in China is is a
piece of watermelon it's not like six
pieces of pie or
something and uh no they they relate to
shika so so it's possible that you have
done a slight kindness to someone else
to help them understand something and
that has created a text which is beyond
your K which is beyond your
understanding okay because sha grow from
small Seas okay that's that's okay
that's easy all
right
uh how about one more these are fun in
book is
hard this one has a budha on it
okay good it's a nice
question I am having experience that I'm
am not sure where it fits into the map
when I am focused on my teacher I feel a
rush of energy this initially feels
wonderful however soon my body tightens
down and I feel like I'm having a
seizure uh this feels like too much so I
have been softening my intensity when I
begin to feel the rush but then I slip
into what feels like a dullness by
comparison is that does that Rush have
any place in where we are trying to go
is there a way to ride the rush without
having a
seizure
uh this is where you this is why we've
been doing yoga okay I mean this is what
in the in the yoga we've been talking
about the inner
body and uh
the the very most
important uh well yeah probably the most
important teaching in on the inner body
which is given in the tiban tradition of
yoga is Lupa right so you've heard that
L you can't say it dang uh l l means
Prana l means the chi in your body
s means your mind your thoughts jupa cha
means they always ride in tandem they
always come in tandem okay your thoughts
are always tied to your Prana and your
Prana is always tied to your thoughts
your Prana is like the horse and the
thoughts are like the horse rider and
it's an interesting relationship if you
if you reflect on
it sometimes the horse is the boss and
sometimes the writer is the boss right I
mean I I people said oh Gish Mak you're
from Arizona I said yeah said you must
be good with horses I said yeah I rode I
rode them twice you know and they said
well why only twice I said well the
first time they gave me this half dead
animal that it was old and they put a
saddle on it and they put me on there
and it kind of
like it kind of like I don't know
tottered down the trail and I was a good
time I wrote on I was
scared uh but I wrote on it I was like
10 or something and then uh later in
college uh somebody put me on a
racehorse and uh it took off and then I
I just went like this you know I went
and then it stopped right there and then
I flew like amazing distance and
uh and then I never got on a horse again
uh so sometimes the horse directs the
show and then in theory the rider can
tell the horse where to go and it's the
same with the inner body so because Lup
because The Prana and the thoughts ride
in Tandem and the thoughts are riding on
The Prana you
can normally you can direct the Prana
with your thoughts so in niguma yoga you
direct The Prana to the inside of the
chakras by focusing there okay and then
that brings The Prana
there uh but the opposite is also true
so normally the horse rider tells the
horse where to go but the principle
behind yoga in Tibet and in Ancient
India is that you you take advantage of
the
relationship to direct The Thoughts by
directing The Prana see so you use you
direct The Prana through certain
movements Asus and then knowing which
channels relate to which emotions you
can elicit emotions by moving Prana okay
so you in that case you're moving the
horse to move the rider you get the
horse to go right and the rider being on
the horse has no choice but to go right
okay so you can you can work the
relationship both ways okay what does it
have to do with meditation
um in meditation you are focusing the
mind in a way which it is never focused
in in normal life okay you are you are
bringing the mind in prara you are
focusing the mind
inwards which has a corresponding effect
on The
Prana okay if you if you concentrate the
Mind inward if you draw the Mind inward
to a
core then that's necessarily drawing The
Prana also into a core because of Lup
because they ride in ger if the horse is
brought into the middle of the barn uh
the rider must come so uh in meditation
the rider is going into the middle of
the barn so the horse has to go with the
rider assuming they're like glued
together with crazy glue or something
okay which is the case they're never
separated
so when you focus the Mind inward during
meditation it would
be it would be very much to be expected
that you should have certain rushes
caused by movements of Prana because The
Prana is linked to the thoughts which
are now being concentrated into the core
of the mind so you would have some kind
of uh you could expect some rushes you
might feel
jolts or you might feel Thrills up your
spine or you might get get these things
you know like that and and that's a
normal result of the thoughts being
concentrated okay
so when you're meditating on your
teacher and you have some kind of Rush
of PR like that whatever mistakes you
make in the meditation whatever dullness
you have or whatever agitation you
have
will you'll have a corresponding
pronic feeling in your body okay so if
you for example I believe the person who
wrote it is over concentrating the mind
right and we talked about it and that
leads to leads to subtle agitation that
leads to gross and subtle agitation so I
would say that the person has overly
brought the mind in and then there's
been a there's been a reaction of the
mind of over excitement over what do you
call it stimulation and then they've had
a corresponding pronic experience so how
do you fix
it which leads us to the question of L
which we talk
about we have four
minutes
uh L is the Tibetan word for Prana okay
we should talk about it longer I'll
start tonight we'll continue tomorrow L
is the tobat word for Prana it also
means wind in Tibet it's also the
element
wind uh like that those are the
different meanings of L uh it's the word
that the Tibetans chose to use to
translate PR the word
PR but if you know about the values the
five values in the yoga in the yoga
schools uh there's not only a Prana
there's all The Prana of the body when
the body needs to do something like
digest food or poop or send Blood Out to
the limbs or cough uh then Prana the the
the general Prana of the body will
collect in that area to perform its
function when The Prana collects in a
specific area to perform a bodily
function we call that a V all the all
those Pras joining together in a
particular area of the body to enunciate
words for example UD V uh they those
those individual PR is collecting here
that becomes a v UD and that projects
words for example or spit or breath
exhalation of breath
so when what is it called there's a
thing called prano okay uh which so you
have to distinguish you have to learn a
disting between Prana Val and Prana okay
Prana Val is one of the five Wings
around the heart area but Prana is all
the energy in the whole body okay so
Prana V is different from Prana okay
uh unfortunately in tibetan they don't
have separate words for Prana and Val so
they end up calling Prana Val the wind
of
wind and and Prana is called wind
General Prana is called wind the V are
called also called wind and the pr is
called the wind of wind so it gets
terrible
uh when you have a
disorder because you have uh
concentrated the mind too strongly
inside without proper training or
without proper breaks or without uh
seeing some kind of vast sky or
something if you concentrate the mind in
too far you get a disorder which is also
called L okay it's given the same name
the disorder of the of
the the disorder of the wind of the wind
is called the wind so you can get the
wind of the wind of the
wind and it's all called Loom and then
it's really confusing but luckily the
Sanskrit words are all different uh so
anyway a disorder of the Prav is called
LOM and uh it it comes from improperly
meditating usually meditating too hard
trying too hard concentrating the mind
in too hard without a feeling of
expensiveness uh or
pleasure okay it's where you feel
uptight you are you are trying to
meditate and you're uptight and rather
than feeling you are feeling anxiety
that you haven't got 28 minutes of
meditation done yet you know it's that
it's that kind of guilt and anxiety and
nervousness
and and then it manifests in a whole
pile of different ways the reason we've
been doing the massages for example was
to try to be proactive about that and
try not to get people not let people
have it that's why we've been getting up
later than
4:00 uh and that's a judgment call by
the teacher if the teacher sees that the
students are all exhausted from three
months of dying at Diamond Mountain then
then they don't get up at 4:00 because
then everybody would get pronav value
disorder uh so maybe the next Retreat we
will when you're all recovered but then
you'll be exhausted from building the
Temple in Phoenix
uh but
uh so what the person is describing the
rush with their teacher and could they
Ride The Rush with their teacher I would
guess that um the feeling of seizure
that they described is uh is the
overactivity of The
Prana uh caused by uh too much
concentration of the mind and and
feeling anxiety over meditating good
enough or something like so then the the
fix for that would be some kind of
spaciousness so uh I would say if if I
were having that kind of Rush with my
teacher you know in the visualization of
my teacher then I would try to lighten
up they described that they were
lightening up but then they felt it went
into dullness that's normal you you turn
the wheel and you go too far and then
you come back so you just have to get
good at um what do you call
it there's a word
compensation you know compens it's like
when you do a twist and you take a what
do they call
it
a you take a Twist to make up for the
first twist you hold this twist for five
breaths and then you do a a
little
anyway uh I'll think of it by
um counter
twist so you would have to do that with
your mind you see you you would have to
do a
counter uh you have to do keep doing
counter twists you know so that person I
would say you're I I would guess that
your main problem is trying too hard and
then look at the Blue Sky uh look at the
valley take yourself to the sky the
valley that's why we do it in the room
with the valy in the sky cuz you
whenever you feel a seizure coming on
you can look at the sky and that's a
traditional method
of
expansiveness uh count counteracts is
the counter twist to over concentration
of the mind okay so try that and then
when you
get then when you start to get dull from
that come back to the golden room okay
so it's a this
thing okay but definitely don't stay
anywhere that's painful or causing
anxiety you got to take action right if
you stay in a place of anxiety or pain
or
trouble or feeling tightness in your
chest and you don't take action then
you've committed problem number
four okay you you're required to do
something about it you're not allowed to
sit in a meditation and feel bad that's
that's not allowed you're supposed to do
something uh so that means you have to
be able to diagnose your own problem and
then give yourself a
prescription all right and and you
should learn to do that you should be
able to diagnose oh I'm having subtle
dullness now what was the fix for that
oh I was supposed to uplift my mind how
was I supposed to do that oh you could
either you could either have just a a
mental of of golden
light or you could start thinking about
how lucky you are to be here and to have
a teacher like that like that just
thinking how lucky you are to have the
teacher that you have uh should be
enough to uplift you anytime okay so
like that you got to know the problems
and you got to know the antidotes and
that's why we're going through them
okay we'll come back to this difficult
part of scripture
tomorrow maybe it will change
right if you do yoga we probably
change good questions though really good
questions very uh classical questions
they've been asked for 2,000
years are you can you do it okay
[Music]
and for